# **Yizhou Shan**

Ph.D. Student School of Electrical and Computer Engineering Purdue University ys@purdue.edu (765) 337-0133 lastweek.io

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests span Operating System, Distributed System, and Computer Architecture, with a focus on building fast and reliable systems for datacenters. I work at Wuklab, Purdue ECE, under the supervision of Prof. Yiying Zhang.

#### **EDUCATION**

Purdue University
Ph.D. in Computer Engineering
(expected)

Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences

Research Assistant

2014-2016

**Beijing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics** 

B.E. in Computer Engineering

2010-2014

#### INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Research Intern, VMware Research

Palo Alto, CA, Summer 2018

Mentor: Dr. Stanko Novakovic

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Stanko Novakovic, **Yizhou Shan**, Aasheesh Kolli, Michael Cui, Yiying Zhang, Haggai Eran, Liran Liss, Michael Wei, Dan Tsafrir, Marcos Aguilera, "Storm: a fast distributed storage system using remote memory primitives", 12th ACM International Systems and Storage Conference (**SYSTOR** '19)

**Yizhou Shan,** Yutong Huang, Yilun Chen, Yiying Zhang, "LegoOS: A Disseminated, Distributed OS for Hardware Resource Disaggregation", 13th USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation (*OSDI '18*) (**Best Paper Award**)

**Yizhou Shan**, Shin-Yeh Tsai, Yiying Zhang, "Distributed Shared Persistent Memory", Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing 2017 (*SoCC* '17)

#### WORKSHOPS AND POSTERS

**Yizhou Shan**, Yutong Huang, Yiying Zhang, "Challenges in Building and Deploying Disaggregated Persistent Memory", 10th Annual Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (*NVMW '19*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Shin-Yeh Tsai, Yiying Zhang, "Distributed Shared Persistent Memory", 9th Annual Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (*NVMW '18*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Yiying Zhang, "Disaggregating Memory with Software-Managed Virtual Cache", the 2018 Workshop on Warehouse-scale Memory Systems (*WAMS '18*) (co-located with ASPLOS '18)

Yiying Zhang, **Yizhou Shan**, Sumukh Hallymysore, "Disaggregated Operating System", 17th International Workshop on High Performance Transaction Systems (*HPTS '17*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Yilun Chen, Yutong Huang, Sumukh Hallymysore, Yiying Zhang, "Lego: A Distributed, Decomposed OS for Resource Disaggregation", Poster at the 26th ACM Symposium on Operating Systems Principles (*SOSP '17*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Sumukh Hallymysore, Yutong Huang, Yilun Chen, Yiying Zhang, "Disaggregated Operating System", Poster at the ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing 2017 (*SoCC '17*)

#### **AWARDS**

OSDI '18 Jay Lepreau Best Paper Award

OSDI '18 Student Travel Grant

SOSP '17 Student Travel Grant

SoCC '17 Student Travel Grant

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## **Disaggregated Operating System**

Purdue University

We propose a new OS model called the splitkernel to manage disaggregated systems. Splitkernel disseminates traditional OS functionalities into loosely-coupled monitors, each of which runs on and manages a hardware component. Using the splitkernel model, we built LegoOS, a new OS designed for hardware resource disaggregation.

#### **Distributed Shared Persistent Memory**

2016-2017

Purdue University

We propose Distributed Shared Persistent Memory (DSPM), a new framework for using persistent memories in datacenter environments. We designed and implemented *Hotpot*, the first DSPM system in Linux kernel. Hotpot provides low-latency, transparent memory accesses, data persistence, data reliability and high availability.

### Non-Volatile Memory (NVM) Emulator

2015-2016

Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences

We designed and implemented a NVM emulator in Linux kernel, which leverages Intel's Performance Monitoring Unit to emulate NVM's slower read/write latency and smaller bandwidth on physical DRAM. This emulator runs on baremetal x86 machines.

ARMv8 CPU Project 2013

Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences

I participated in the Register-Transfer Level design and verification of some blocks within cache unit and load-store unit. It is commercial project collaborated with Huawei.

2017-2018